Guide to the Elliott Maxwell Sanger Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Elliott Maxwell Sanger Papers,
1936-1986
Sanger, Elliott M.
3 linear ft. (ca. 200 items in 8 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079590
Biographical Note
Elliott Maxwell Sanger, 1897-, was a co-founder of radio station WQXR in 1936 and executive vice-president and general manager of the station from 1936-1965.
Scope and Content
Included are Sanger's personal diaries (1936-1967) relating to WQXR. Also included is a complete bound file of the WQXR PROGRAM GUIDE (June 1936-December 1963) containing a record of the broadcasting of classical music in New York City, the daily schedule, and essays on composers, music festivals, individual compositions and music in general by such writers as Irwin Edman, Will Durant, M. Lincoln Schuster, Edward Johnson, John Barbirolli, as well as by Sanger and his co-founder, John V. L. Hogan. There are also four tape recordings of radio broadcast interviews with Mr. Sanger aired in 1973.
1980 Addition: A selected file of approximately 150 letters, manuscripts, documents, photographs and printed materials relating to the history of radio station WQXR. There are business letters, congratulatory and testimonial letters from listeners and advertisers, including one each from Will Durant and Sinclair Lewis, office memoranda and reports on the station's history, samples of newspaper clippings containing WQXR advertisements and program listings, market surveys of listeners and promotional brochures prepared for prospective advertisers. There is a corrected typescript and galley proofs for Sanger's book, REBEL IN RADIO (N.Y., Hastings House, 1972), and 6 volumes of documents in support of the station's application for "clear channel" status filed with the Federal Communications Commission in 1948. Also included are 49 photographs of the station's staff, musical personalities who have broadcasted, the studios and transmitters, 4 audio cassettes celebrating WQXR's 50th anniversary, the anniversary album, and the anniversary edition of REBEL IN RADIO.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Rebel In Radio
Series III: WQXR
Series IV: Personal Papers
Subjects
United States.--Federal Communications Commission.; WQXR (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); Durant, Will, 1885-1981.; Edman, Irwin, 1896-1954.; Hogan, John V.L.; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951.; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968.; Music.; Music radio stations--New York (State)--New York.; Radio--Transmitters and transmission.; Radio advertising--New York (State)--New York.; Radio broadcasting--New York (State)--New York.; Radio stations--New York (State)--New York.; Advertisements.; Albums.; Audio cassettes.; Audio tapes.; Brochures.; Diaries.; Galley proofs.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Reports.; Surveys.; Businessmen.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-7. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1979 M-1979 Sanger, E.M. Gift
Gift of Elliott M. Sanger, 1979-1980 & 1986.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - The series contains correspondence related to Sanger's radio station, WQXR, from Will Durant, Arthur Sulzberger, and Sinclair Lewis.A-Z, 1937-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Rebel In Radio
  - The series contains materials related to Elliot Sanger's book Rebel in Radio, 1973., [1973], (Typescript, photographs, galley proof) (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Sanger interview by Andre Bernard, April 12, 1973: Sanger Interview with P.M. Program by Bill Newcastle, September 29, 1973, (2 reel to reel audio tapes) (Box 1)
  - WQXR Broadcast, May 24, 1973, 10-12 Noon, 2 reels: "The Listening Room" hosted by Robert Sherman -- Guest, E. M. Sanger, (2 reel to reel audio tapes) (Box 2)
- Series III: WQXR
  The series contains files related to Sanger's radio station, WQXR
  - FCC "Clear Channel" Hearings, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - File 1-2): -- FCC "Clear Channel" Hearings, 1946; File 3)-- Letters, 1936-1948; File 4-5)-- Market Research Survey, 1936-1944; File 6)-- Newspaper clippings, 1936; File 7)-- Photographs; File 8)-- Sales records, 1936-1948, 1936-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Remembrances and background material: 1986 anniversary program, 1936-1950, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "This Is My Music" with Elliot Sanger, March 1, 1986 -- New York Philharmonic 50th Anniversary Concert, September 23, 1986 -- Part I and II -- WQXR Dinner Comments, September 23, 1986, (4 audio cassettes) (Box 7)
  - , 1936-1963, (27 volumes) (Box 3-5)
- Series IV: Personal Papers
  - Diaries, 1936-1967, (32 volumes) (Box 5-7)
  - Key to Abbreviations beginning 1950 (Box 6)
  - "In Memoriam: Elliott M. Sanger,", 1989 (Box 7)